Previously on the show.
Episode sebelumnya.
The goats took the magic train and set off to the sky.
Para kambing naik kereta ajaib dan pergi ke langit.
On their way, they were attacked by Sirius.
Dalam perjalanan, mereka diserang Sirius.
During the fight, Wolnie's precious stone
Saat bertarung, batu berharga Wolnie tiba-tiba bersikap tak teratur
and caused a huge explosion.
dan memicu ledakan besar.
What fate awaits the goats?
Nasib apa yang menanti para kambing?
"Flying Island: The Sky Adventure: Meeting the Mechanical Bird."
Petualangan Langit: Pulau Terbang. Bertemu dengan Burung Mekanik.
What is this?
Apa ini?
It's gone.
Hilang.
Where am I?
Di mana aku?
You're awake!
Kau sudah siuman.
Who are you?
Siapa kau?
My name is Auntie Bowie. I saved your life.
Aku Bibi Bowie. Aku penyelamatmu.
Thank you, Auntie Bowie.
Terima kasih, Bibi Bowie.
My name is Weslie. There's something...
Namaku Weslie. Ada sesuatu...
Would you like something to eat? I'll be right back.
Kau mau makan? Aku segera kembali.
Auntie Bowie, I would like to ask about my friends...
Bibi Bowie, aku ingin bertanya tentang temanku...
Here, hold this.
Ini, ambillah.
Don't hold back. Eat as much as you like.
Jangan malu. Makan yang banyak.
Umm, I'd like to ask...
Aku mau tanya...
Don't talk when you're eating.
Jangan bicara saat makan.
Come on. Let's dig in together.
Ayo kita makan bersama.
Auntie Bowie, I would like to...
Bibi Bowie, aku mau...
Would you like some dessert?
Mau pencuci mulut?
No... I just want to know where my friends are.
Bukan. Aku cuma mau tahu di mana teman-temanku.
Friends?
Teman?
These are my friends. Have you seen them?
Ini teman-temanku. Kau melihatnya?
No. When I saved you, you were alone.
Tidak. Saat aku menyelamatkanmu, kau sendirian.
Afterward, I didn't see any goats.
Aku tak lihat ada kambing lain.
Really? Would they have been captured by Wolffy?
Sungguh? Apa mereka ditangkap Wolffy?
I must go and find them now.
Aku harus cari mereka.
Don't run around when you can't fly.
Jangan asal berkeliaran di langit.
Our Tower Town is 5,000 meters above the ground.
Kota Menara kami 5.000 meter di atas tanah.
What? Five thousand meters above the ground?
Apa? 5.000 meter di atas tanah?
Village Chief and the rest must be in danger then.
- Kepala Desa dan yang lain dalam bahaya! - Tenang!
They must have fallen into other cloud cities just like you.
Mereka pasti jatuh ke kota awan lain sepertimu.
Other cloud cities?
Kota awan lain?
This sky has many other cities on the clouds.
Di langit ada banyak kota awan lainnya.
These clouds are very strong.
Awannya sangat kuat.
Your friends will be fine even if they fall on the clouds.
Temanmu akan aman walau jatuh di awan.
That's a relief then.
Syukurlah.
Is there a way to get to other cloud cities?
Ada cara untuk menuju kota awan lain?
You have to ask our mechanical master for that.
Kau harus tanya master mekanik kami.
We are in the clouds. This is great!
Kita ada di atas awan. Ini hebat!
Dad...
Ayah...
Dad... look. I'm the village chief now.
Ayah, lihat. Kini aku kepala desa.
Look, me too.
Ayah juga.
That's right.
Benar.
Wilie, go and play. Dad and I have something to talk about.
Willie, pergilah bermain. Ayah dan Ibu harus berbicara.
Wolffy, come with me.
Wolffy, ikut aku.
Wolffy, how did my birthday party go so wrong?
Kenapa pesta ulang tahunku jadi kacau?
Wolnie, consider this as a family event.
Wolnie, anggap ini acara keluarga.
Look, I'm Paddi now.
Lihat, aku Paddi sekarang.
I want to go home!
Aku mau pulang!
But Sirius is gone.
Tapi Sirius hilang.
Fine, I'll figure this out.
Baik, akan kucari tahu caranya.
-Auntie Bowie, can we go now? -I'm coming...
- Bibi Bowie, sudah boleh pergi? - Aku datang...
This is so cute.
Ini manis sekali.
Let's go!
- Ayo! - Bibi Bowie, ada pencuri.
There's no one there.
Tak ada orang di sana.
Weslie, did you see something?
Tunggu, kau lihat sesuatu?
Let's go.
Ayo.
You're new here,
Kau baru di sini, jadi ada tiga hal yang harus kau ingat.
What are they?
Apa itu?
First, never judge us. Birds are bad singers.
Pertama, jangan menghakimi kami. Burung adalah penyanyi buruk.
The singing is horrible.
Nyanyiannya parah sekali.
What did you say?
Apa katamu?
Beat him! Don't let him get away!
Hajar dia! Kejar!
Second, watch out for loose clouds...
Kedua, waspada pada awan yang longgar...
What's going on?
Apa yang terjadi?
...as well as the cloud-pressing trucks that solidifies cloud surfaces.
...serta truk penggilas awan yang memperkuat permukaan.
Lastly, never bully young birds.
Terakhir, jangan merisak burung muda.
Their mothers are very scary.
Ibu mereka amat menakutkan.
What are you looking at?
Apa yang kau lihat?
Haven't you seen a handsome wolf before?
Belum lihat serigala ganteng?
I will be back!
Aku akan kembali!
We've arrived. The master lives here.
Sudah sampai. Master tinggal di sini.
Master!
Master!
You've got the wrong guy.
Kau salah orang.
His name is Potato. He's the master's assistant.
Namanya Kentang. Dia adalah asisten Master.
Master is over there.
Master ada di sana.
He's the master?
Dia masternya?
Auntie Bowie, I saw him stealing spare parts just now.
Bibi, tadi aku lihat dia mencuri suku cadang.
You've misunderstood. Master was merely collecting scraps.
Kau salah paham. Master hanya mencari barang bekas.
Auntie Bowie, who do you have there?
Bibi Bowie, kau bersama siapa?
His name is Weslie. He got separated from his friends.
Ini Weslie. Dia terpisah dari teman-temannya.
Could you help him get to other cloud cities?
Bisa bantu dia ke kota awan lain?
This looks familiar.
Tampak tak asing.
Have you seen them?
Kau lihat mereka?
I have the same pair of glasses as this goat.
Aku punya kacamata yang sama dengan dia.
Don't make jokes. Please help Weslie.
Jangan melawak. Tolong, bantu Weslie.
Sure, no problem.
Tentu, tak masalah.
Weslie, Master has agreed to help you.
Weslie, Master setuju membantumu.
Potato, I'll hand Weslie over to you.
Kentang, kuserahkan Weslie kepadamu.
Bro, if you want to go to other cloud cities,
Kak, jika mau ke kota awan lain, pakai saja pesawat besarku.
Where's the big plane?
- Di mana pesawatnya? - Ada di sini.
The plane is too big, it's covered in clouds.
Pesawatnya terlalu besar, tertutup awan.
-What's wrong? -It's fine... My plane is under repair.
- Ada apa? - Tak apa. Pesawatku sedang diperbaiki.
How long will that take?
Butuh waktu berapa lama?
It's still 365 days away from being ready.
Masih butuh 365 hari lagi hingga siap.
I think I had better find another way to leave this place.
Sebaiknya aku cari cara lain untuk pergi.
Wait.
Tunggu. Pesawatku punya banyak fungsi. Bisa akurat mencari lokasi temanmu.
Are you sure you still want to leave?
- Yakin tetap mau pergi? - Sungguh?
Of course. Let me give you a tour.
Tentu. Kuantar berkeliling.
Why is the toilet right next to the entrance?
Kenapa toiletnya dekat pintu masuk?
This is not the toilet. This is my cockpit.
Ini bukan toilet.  Ini kokpit.
Come. Look.
Ayo. Lihat.
This is an extra seat.
Yang ini kursi ekstra.
And this is my pilot seat.
Yang ini kursi pilotku.
It might look shabby, but it comes with a seatbelt.
Mungkin tampak lusuh, tapi ada sabuk pengaman.
Its only weakness is it's tough to tear.
Satu-satunya kelemahan adalah sulit robek.
Would you like to try?
Mau coba?
No, thanks.
Tidak perlu.
This lollipop is actually the steering stick.
Lolipop ini sebenarnya tongkat kemudi.
Isn't this too primitive?
Ini tak terlalu kuno?
We can't help it. We don't have enough spare parts.
Terpaksa Tak ada cukup suku cadang.
But I'm sure the next function will impress you.
Tapi fungsi berikutnya pasti akan membuatmu terkesan.
Let me ask you.
Aku mau tanya. Apa fungsi terpenting sebuah pesawat?
-The autopilot system? -No.
- Sistem autopilot? - Tidak.
The most important function is of course, karaoke.
Fungsi terpentingnya adalah karaoke.
Trips can be boring. How can we not have entertainment?
Bepergian bisa membosankan. Bagaimana bisa tak ada hiburan?
Where's Weslie?
Mana Weslie?
Master is unreliable.
Master tak bisa diandalkan.
Weslie, there're still a lot of functions I haven't shown you yet.
Weslie, masih ada banyak fungsi lainnya.
When I get Sirius back, you birds will be in trouble.
Saat aku dapat Sirius kembali, kalian akan dalam masalah.
Sirius!
Sirius!
What happened to Sirius?
Apa yang terjadi padamu?
What is this?
Apa ini?
Why am I so unlucky today?
Kenapa aku begitu sial?
What now?
Sekarang apa?
A plane? This is great!
Pesawat terbang? Hebat! Bisa bawa pulang Wolnie dan Willie.
But this plane is a bit strange.
Tapi, pesawat ini agak aneh.
Never mind. I'll fix it after flying home.
Tak apa. Akan kuperbaiki setelah terbang pulang.
It even has this function.
Bahkan ada fungsi ini.
Awesome! Let me get Wolnie while I sing.
Hebat! Biar kujemput Wolnie sambil bernyanyi.
Weslie, here you are.
Rupanya kau di sini.
Let's go back. I'm not done introducing the plane yet.
Aku belum selesai tunjukkan pesawat.
-But... -My big plane is fantastic.
- Tapi... - Pesawat besarku fantastis.
It's not only big, but can also fly very fast.
Bukan hanya besar, tapi bisa terbang cepat.
See how fast it's flying?
Lihat kecepatannya?
Why is my plane flying?
Kenapa pesawatku terbang?
Let's go after it.
Ayo kita kejar.
We can't reach the plane at all.
Kita tak bisa dekati pesawat.
Don't worry. I used spare parts that fell from the plane and made a sucker gun.
Tenang. Ada suku cadang yang jatuh dari pesawat dan kubuat senjata.
Awesome!
Luar biasa!
Safe landing. Let's go in.
Pendaratan aman. Ayo masuk.
So Weslie is here too.
Ada Weslie juga.
I shall capture you as well.
Aku akan menangkapmu juga.
Where's the weapon?
Di mana senjatanya?
You're not singing anymore?
Kau sudah tak nyanyi lagi.
Sing? I have to catch the goat.
Menyanyi? Aku harus tangkap kambing.
Who are you? How long have you been here?
Siapa kau? Sudah berapa lama di sini?
I am Donald Potato. I've heard you sing three songs.
Aku Donald Kentang. Kudengar kau bernyanyi tiga lagu.
Why didn't you say anything then?
Kenapa kau tak memberitahuku?
Because Auntie Bowie said not to talk when you're eating.
Karena Bibi Bowie melarang bicara saat makan.
Why are you talking now?
Kenapa kini bicara?
Because I finished my food.
Karena makananku habis.
Wolffy!
Wolffy!
Wolffy, hand the plane back to Master.
Wolffy, kembalikan pesawatnya pada Master.
This is my plane.
Ini pesawatku. Jangan coba mengambilnya.
Take that!
Rasakan itu!
I'm the real owner of this plane. Potato, pour the oil.
Aku pemilik asli pesawat ini. Kentang, tuang olinya.
Goodbye, Mr. Wolffy.
Selamat tinggal, Pak Wolffy.
Here, this is yours.
Ini untukmu.
I'm so glad to see you've become friends.
Aku senang lihat kalian sudah berteman.
Dig in. I'm going now. Goodbye.
Makanlah. Aku pergi sekarang. Sampai jumpa.
Master, you're amazing.
Master, kau hebat, tapi kenapa pesawatmu masih lusuh?
That's because Tower Town have too few spare parts.
Karena Kota Menara punya sedikit suku cadang.
Master, I found some spare parts.
Guru, aku menemukan beberapa suku cadang.
Isn't this from the magic train?
Bukankah ini dari kereta ajaib?
TO BE CONTINUED 0365 DAYS FROM SETTING SAIL
BERSAMBUNG 365 HARI SEBELUM PULANG